<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true coppie of the declaration published at Sanqhair upon the tenth day of August 1692</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95018</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2642</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229925</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895733</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895733</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153370</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95018)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2360:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true coppie of the declaration published at Sanqhair upon the tenth day of August 1692</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year M.DC.XCIII. [1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Drop-head title on page 3: The declaration of a poor wasted, misrepresented remnant, of the suffering, anti-popish, anti-prelatick, anti-erastian, anti-sectarian, true presbyterian church of Christ, in Scotland, united together in a generall correspondence. Published at Sanqhair.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153370:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> True Coppie of the DECLARATION <hi>Published at</hi> SANQHAIR <hi>Upon the tenth day of Auguſt</hi> 1692.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Sic enim omninò ſtatuo, Non ideo interire in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia veritatem, etiamſi ab uno Concilio oppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur: Sed mirabiliter à Domino ſervari, ut iterum ſuo tempore emergat &amp; ſuperet.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Calvin.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year M.DC.XCIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153370:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153370:2"/>
            <head>THE DECLARATION Of a Poor waſted, miſrepreſented Remnant, of the ſuffering, Anti-Popiſh, Anti-Prelatick, Anti-Eraſtian, Anti-Sectarian, True Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Church of Chriſt, IN SCOTLAND, United together in a Generall Correſpondence <hi>Published at</hi> SANQHAIR.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T will, no doubt, be reputed by many, a work both ſuperfluous and Unſeaſonable at this time, to publiſh any thing of this Nature. Superfluous, in regard that our Principles and practiſes are already abundantly manifeſt to the world, particularly in our <hi>Informatory Vindication, The Teſtimony againſt the Toleration,</hi> and the Contendings and ſufferings of many of our dear brethren in their adhering to the ſame. And unſeaſonable, by reaſon of our preſent Circumſtances, being this day as ſheep ſcattered upon the mountains, without a ſheep-herd to gather or lead us: No man taking care for our ſouls: But in ſtead thereof, all or moſt part waiting for our halting, Looking for and Lying in wait, to catch Advantage againſt the Cauſe, through the leaſt miſbehaviour of any of thoſe who oun it: And would, we doubt not, be glad of any thing whereby they might get the leaſt ſhaddow of ground to reproach; Now when we are as <hi>ſignes</hi> and <hi>wonders,</hi> and have for moe to Criticize upon our words and actions, than to kyth any Sympathy with the ſcope and deſigne of what we intend by the ſame. Upon theſe and the like conſiderations, it may be a queſtion, whether at this time it be our duty to appear in this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153370:3"/>manner? Seing much of the Beauty and Luſtre of a Teſtimony, yea and much of its weight, depends upon its being both ſeaſonably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited, and by men of underſtanding, that have knowledge of the times, and what <hi>Iſrael</hi> ought to doe. Theſe and many other things relative to the ſame, as they have in ſome meaſure been pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by us; ſo have not altogether wanted their oun weight, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr us from any thing of this nature in ſuch a Juncture. But yet u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the other hand, When we conſider, that ever ſince the Lords Outſtretched Arm brought redemption to this Land from Anti-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Darkneſs, and in ane eminent way made it his oun, by bringing us under theſe Sacred and Inviolable Bonds of holy Covenants; As E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to that Covenanted work of Reformation, have not been, neither at this day are wanting for their part, in carrying on their Malignant Deſignes, in Oppoſition to and for deſtruction of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Cauſe of God, and have been not a litle helped thereto by the faintings and Daſtardly yeeldings of Unfaithfull and Declyning Miniſters and Profeſſors of the ſame. So Likewiſe, the Lord hath glorifyed his Name, and hath ſo far Dignified this Church, as to have the honour (to the honour of his Name be it ſpoken) of having ſtill a Party in her, who notwithſtanding the Helliſh Cruelty of open and avowed Enemies in their perſecution on the one hand, and the baſe and treacherous Dealings of backſlyding Miniſters and Profeſſors in their Reproaches and Miſrepreſentations of that poor Party on the other hand. Yet over all theſe Difficulties, accounted it their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be faithfull for him in their places and ſtations: And eſteemed the leaſt <hi>hoof</hi> of the attained unto Reformation, preferrable to their Deareſt Intereſts: Laid hold upon all opportunities that were offered for giving a Teſtimony of their Love to himſelf, and zeal for his Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Glory, although ſeldome or never thought ſeaſonable by the wiſe and Learned <hi>Rabbies</hi> of the time. Conſidering how they were helped to reſiſt unto blood, in ſtriving to <hi>keep the word of his patience,</hi> and <hi>contend for the faith once Delivered to the Saints.</hi> How the Lord ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon their honeſt Deſignes, and received them with good-will at their hands. And Likwiſe conſidering, what God-provocking, ſoul-enſnaring, and Land-Deſolating Courſes are now on foot in theſe Lands; as if all we have done theſe years bypaſt were not ſufficient to Draw doun the Lords deſerved wrath upon us, without putting on the Capeſtone on all our other defections, <hi>by Joyning once more in Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with the people of theſe Abominations,</hi> and carrying it on under the Name of <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>New Reformation.</hi> And then, what ſtrange Apprehenſions the Land hath conceived of us, upon the account of our non-concurrence with the ſame, looking upon us as <hi>men mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſled, drinking in and mentaining ſtrange and pernicious principles, Deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of Government, and Rejecters of the Goſpell.</hi> We ſay, upon theſe and other weighty Conſiderations, we Judge our ſelves ſome way obliged, if we can do no more, at leaſt to kyth our deſire to follow that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153370:3"/>
               <hi>Noble cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> and to go forth by their footſteps in conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for <hi>Truth,</hi> by adding our mite of a Teſtimony to all the <hi>Truths</hi> that are this day Practicallie Controverted: and againſt all defections either on right or Left hand, whatſoever plauſible pretences they may be covered with. Although we judge our ſelves, at this time, Incapable of Publiſhing any thing that can either make Truth more clear than it is, or yet eſcape the ſneaking Cenſure of thoſe, whoſe ſtation (if they were faithfull in it) Leads them to be far more forward in this work than we.</p>
            <p>We therefore Declare to the world, our hearty deſire to embrace and adhere to the written <hi>Word of God,</hi> contained in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the <hi>Old and New Teſtament,</hi> as the only and compleat Rule of Faith and Manners: And whatſoever is founded thereupon, or ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable thereunto, ſuch as <hi>Our Confeſſion of Faith, Larger and ſhorter Catechiſms, Directory for Worſhip, Our Covenants, National and Solemne League, The Acknowledgment of Sins, and Engadgment to Duties, Cauſes of Gods Wrath,</hi> The Ordinary and Perpetuall Officers of the Church by Chriſts oun appointment, as <hi>Paſtors, Doctors, Elders</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> and the Form of Church Government, Commonlie called <hi>Presbyterial.</hi> We Declare our Adherence to all the faithfull Contendings for Truth, whether of old or of Late, by Miniſters or Profeſſors, againſt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſinfull Courſes, whether more refined or more groſſe. And particularly, againſt the <hi>Publick Reſolutions, Cromuels Uſurpation,</hi> the <hi>Toleration of Hereſies and Sects</hi> in his time. Againſt the Sacrilegious Uſurpations and Tyranny of <hi>Char.</hi> 2d. The Unfaithfullneſs of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Profeſſors in complying with him, by accepting his Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences firſt or laſt. And in a word, to every thing aggreeable to the Matter of our Teſtimony as it is Declared pag. 25. and 26. of our <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatory Vindication</hi> printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1687. Likewiſe, our adherence to he Teſtimony againſt the abominable <hi>Toleration</hi> granted by the <hi>Duke of York,</hi> given in to the Miniſters at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by that faithfull Miniſter and now glorifyed Martyr <hi>Mr. James Renuick Janr.</hi> 17. 1688. And to whatever faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full contendings have been made, or Teſtimonies given againſt the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eavours of any, in their ſtriving to engadge us in a ſinfull Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie with a Malignant Cauſe, contrary to this our Teſtimony, ſince the Late Revolutions.</p>
            <p>Next, we Declare our Rejecting of whatever is Contradictorie or contrary unto the written Word of God, or not founded therupon either Expreſly, or by Direct, near-or neceſſary Conſequence. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re particularly, we Teſtify our Deteſtation and Abhorrence of <hi>Popery, Quakeriſme, Libertiniſme, Antinomianiſme, Socinianiſme, Anabaptiſme, Independency, Prelacy</hi> and <hi>Eraſtianiſme,</hi> and all Extravagancies and Errors on the right or Left hand, ſuch as the Doting Deluſions of theſe draun into a Conſortſhip in and about the <hi>COTE-MOO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RE.</hi> Together with all Kinds of Idolatry, Superſtition and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanneſſe, and whatſoever is found contrary to ſound Doctrine and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153370:4"/>the Power of Godlineſſe, and againſt every other thing, contrary to the Teſtimony of this Church, as they are particularly enumerated in Page 27. and 28. of our forſaid <hi>Vindication.</hi> And in Like manner we Diſoun as a ſtep of Defection, Declyning from, and contradictory unto the Covenanted Reformation of the Kirk of Scotland, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Teſtimony of our Anceſtours, The Publiſhing of that Declaration, called, <hi>The Declaration of HIS HIGHNESSE WILLIAM PRINCE of ORANGE &amp;c.</hi> And eſpouſing it as the ſtate of the Church and Kingdom of Scotlands Quarrell, while he then was, and yet is, ſurrounded in Counſell and Army with many of the old and Inveterate Enemies of Chriſts Cauſe and people, both at home in theſe Lands and abroad, except France and his Aſſociates. His unconcernedneſſe with the overturning the work of God in theſe Lands theſe many years, till his oun Intereſt, and the Call of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats</hi> in <hi>England</hi> did prompt him to his Undertakings. Their Being ſet up by the Suffrages of theſe men of blood here in Scotland, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of their being Immediately before Crouned and Anointed King and Queen in our Neighbouring Covenanted Land, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all the Engliſh Popiſh Ceremonies, upon their engadging on their knees, before the Altar &amp;c. <hi>To the utmoſt of their power to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve unto the Biſhops and Clergy of that Realme, and to the Churches com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their Charge, ſuch Rites and Priviledges as do or ſhall appertain unto them, or any of them.</hi> As alſo, if we conſider his other Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Reaſons inducing him <hi>to appear in Arms in the Kingdom of England, Scotland and Ireland,</hi> emitted at the ſame time; Wherin he Labours to put ſhame and contempt upon moſt of all the contendings of this Church, and to bury many of the moſt materiall points of her Teſtimony. Thereby declaring his principles, and what he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon in his after practiſe: And his thereby rending and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning that deſirable Uniformity in Religion attained unto with <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> which theſe Lands cannot break without manifeſt Perjury; being ſworn thereto by <hi>the firſt Article of the ſolemne League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi> At Leaſt it is a walking in their Counſels who rent the ſame before him; and an undenyable Corroborating and Ratifying <hi>the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of Omri and the works of the houſe of Ahab,</hi> that thereby theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted Lands ſhould be made a deſolation, and the Inhabitants thereof a hiſſing. Upon theſe and other very weighty grounds and reaſons, which (if the Lord will) we may have the occaſion to make knoun afterwards; We Declare the Refuſal of our Concurrence with the preſent Courſe now on foot; It being no way Concerted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ancient <hi>Plea</hi> of the Scottiſh Covenanters, <hi>for the Covenanted Reformation of Religion in Brittain and Jreland, for the Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government of the Houſe of God, againſt Poperie, Prelacie, Malignancy, Sectarianiſme, Eraſtianiſme, and whatever is contrary to ſound Doctrine and the power of Godlineſſe.</hi> But in ſtead thereof, a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and concurring with the Promotters of all theſe, in their <hi>Popiſh,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153370:4"/>Prelatick, Malignant</hi> and <hi>Sectarian</hi> deſignes, whereby Error, Profani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Wickedneſſe is Encouraged and Tolerated; The Lord highly diſhonoured; His avowed and Declared Enemies brought in to places of greateſt Power and Truſt, in ſtead of bringing the wheel of Juſtice over them; Together with the addition of moſt of all thoſe, who have been the chief Ring-leaders, Fomenters and Favourers of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, Toleration,</hi> and all other Defections of this Church. This quarrel, we ſay, we refuſe to eſpouſe in <hi>Lieu</hi> of that other: But to ſignifie our diſpleaſure therewith, refuſes to concurr in any thing that we know will ſtrengthen or encouradge the ſame, ſuch as taking <hi>the Oath of Aleigance,</hi> Randivouzing at their command, Paying any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies Impoſed for that end, or doing any thing that may tend to the weakening the hands or ſaddening the hearts of our brethren, in their Honeſt, zealous and faithfull contending againſt the ſame. For which Let all concerned ſee <hi>the Seaſonable and Neceſſary warning of the Generall Aſſembly of this Kirk to all the members thereof, July</hi> 27. 1649. <hi>Seſs.</hi> 27. <hi>Gen: Aſſem: July ult</hi> 1648. <hi>Seſs.</hi> 21. <hi>with the Humble Supplication of the Aſſembly to the Committee of Eſtates Auguſt</hi> 2. 1648. <hi>Seſs.</hi> 25. <hi>Act Gener. Aſſem. Aug.</hi> 3. 1648. <hi>Seſs.</hi> 26. <hi>Act</hi> 4. <hi>Parl.</hi> 2. <hi>Char.</hi> And what our Land mourned for <hi>Art.</hi> 9. <hi>Step.</hi> 5. <hi>of the Cauſes of Gods Wrath.</hi> With many places of Scripture, Acts both of Aſſemblies and Parliaments, which are ſo clear, that if they were made judges, and durſt come above-board to examine the preſent Courſe; It were no great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the meaneſt capacitie, to ſee as great diſparity between this and what our Fathers contended for, as between Defection and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. But Leſt we ſhould be hereby ſuſpected of mentaining the Principle of diſouning all Government: Therefore, as for ſuch Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, as, being rightly and Lawfully Conſtitute over us, ſhall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their Power for ſetting the Mediator on His Throne, and the Croun upon His head, and in defence of his Croun-Rights and Royall Prerogatives, ſhall act as the Miniſters of God in a direct Line of Subordination to him, in Defence of our Covenanted Reformation, and the Subjects Liberties, againſt <hi>Popery, Prelacy, Eraſtianiſme, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, Hereſy, Profanneſſe,</hi> and whatever ſhall be found to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to ſound Doctrine and the Power of Godlineſſe: and thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Terror to evil Doers, and encouragers of them that do well. We Declare, whenſoever we can obtain and enjoy ſuch Rulers, we will Oun, Embrace and Defend them to the utmoſt of our Power, and prove encouraging ſubject and obedient to them in our places and Stations. And here in purſuance of our former Teſtimony, we reſolve to ſtand &amp; wait.</p>
            <p>Moreover, we Teſtify and declare againſt the unparallelled unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſse of the Miniſters in Scotland, as in what they have done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe Revolutions to the detriment of the Cauſe: So eſpeciallie-ſince; in Contributing and Concurring they and their Accomplices, in their ſtations and to their power, with the bulk of theſe Old<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153370:5"/>bloodie and perjured Enemies of Chriſt, his Cauſe and people, in their ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up HIS HIGHNESSE THE PRINCE AND PRIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CESS OF ORANGE, King and Queen over theſe Covenanted Lands, while acting directly contrarie to the Covenants; being wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout Covenant-Qualifications <hi>Viz. of known Integrity, Approven fidelity, Conſtant Affection and zeal to the Cauſe of God, Such againſt whom there is no Juſt Cauſe of exception nor jealouſie;</hi> which our Covenants and the Laws of the Croun require to be in Judges Superiour or Inferiour, whom we are allowed to ſet over us and joyn with, according to <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3, 4. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7.2, 7. Being not of one perfect Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion with our ſelves; neither in Covenant, nor admitted Covenant-wayes: without the ſealing and ſwearing of which, our fathers, or rather we our ſelves, refuſed to receive <hi>Charles the ſecond</hi> to the Croun. It being the very foundation, wherupon any right they have to Govern is founded: And without the Approbation and Subſcription whereof, the people can never have from him, Sufficient ſecurity, either for Religion or their Juſt Liberties. And, if the <hi>Prelats</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> with their Aſsociates, were ſo peremptory, as not to admitt him to the exerciſe of the Government, untill they had him engadged to mentain and defend that Abjured Hierarchie; How Aſtoniſhing is it that <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> ſhould not have waited, till the Lord had raiſed up Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, rightly Qualifyed, and from whom ſufficient Security for the Covenanted Reformation of the True Religion in theſe Lands might be had: and not to have made haſt, in building up <hi>Zions</hi> breaches with the ſtones of that <hi>burnt mountain of</hi> BABYLON? Their unfaithfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to their ſouls, In not repreſenting to them the Hazard they we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and would be in, if they entred themſelves heirs to the ſins of that Throne, againſt which the Lord hath ſuch a Long and Eminent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, In ſeeking to eſtabliſh his oun Intereſt upon the Ruines of the Intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt; which is nothing else, but to oppoſe the Kingdom of the ſon of God, <hi>by whom Kings do reigne.</hi> If he ſhould cleave unto theſe men as his Truſty Counſellors, Who, as they never had the Glory of God nor the good of his People before their eyes; So now, in all their Wayes and Counſels, are ſeeking nothing but their oun Intereſt, to the Hazard and Deſtruction of Religion and the Deſolation of the Kingdoms. If he ſhould ſettle a peace with Gods Avowed and Declared Enemies, the murtherers of his poor innocent People, by ouning them as his good and Loyal Subjects, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>their peacable ſubmiſsion to his Government.</hi> And if he ſhould Employ, Help, Concurr or Joyn with Anti-chriſtian Forces, either at Home or Abroad. All which he hath done, and this day is doing; which cannot be otherwiſe Judged, but a giving of his Royall Power and ſtrength unto the Beaſt: and an acceſſion to all that blood of the Lords people, wherwith thoſe ſons of <hi>Babel</hi> have made the Lands under their Reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Tyrannies to Suim. Their unfaithfullneſs, in not Laying plainly and ſeaſonably to his Conſideration, what the mouth of the LORD
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153370:5"/>of HOSTS hath ſpoken of all the Accounts of People, Nations, Kings, and Rulers againſt the Kingdom of His Son; that they Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne a Vain thing, and that he that ſitteth in Heaven will have them in deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure. What marks of deſperate Malignancie; Enmity and hatred to the Cauſe and people of God, hath appeared, theſe Years bypaſt, in theſe men that now bear the SUAY in his Councels and Armies. How the Anger of the Lord hath been kindled, even againſt his deareſt Saints, when they have joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſuch men as he hateth, and is Curſed. And how ſeverelie he hath threatned and puniſhed ſuch Kings, as have Aſsociate with Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters &amp; Leaned to their helps. And next, Their Unfaithfullneſse to the poor guilty Land, in not forſeeing the Evil and fore ſhewing the Danger, of ſetting up Magiſtrates without aſking Counſell at the mouth of the Lord; Although a Duty Incumbent on faithfull Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to ſet the Trumpet to their mouths in ſuch Caſes, and give Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and Diſtinct Warning, leſt Iſrael caſt off the thing that is good, and the Enemie purſue him, for ſetting up Kings and not by God, and Princes without his knowledge. Nor yet declaring the ſin and Danger of Aſsociating in War with known Enemies of Truth and Godlineſse, ſuch as are employed in the preſent Expedition: Wherby a door is ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the Introduction, Toleration, and Encouragment of <hi>Papiſts, Malignants</hi> and <hi>Sectaries;</hi> And the ſtate of the Quarrell, in ſtead of being rightly propoſed, according to the Ancient PLEA, againſt both right and left hand oppoſites; it is therby betrayed, loſt and buryed. Add to all theſe, their pretended Faſts and Thankſgivings, for Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and proſperity to the Enemies of God, his Church and people: Whereby the Lord is mocked, His Truths buryed, The peoples Souls enſnared, The Godly ſtumbled, A Courſe of Reformation rather bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed than raiſed, proſecuted or defended, And a Malignant Quarrell embraced; Yea that ſame Courſe which hath been alwayes Curſt of God, and upon which he hath ſet evident marks of his Diſpleaſure. The Publick Sin, for which he is this day contending againſt the Land: and the ACHAN which hath made <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſo oft to fall before their Enemies.</p>
            <p>Now, if this be no falſe Charge, as, Alace! it is not: And if the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe be not only pieces of unfaithfullneſse, but manifeſt breaches of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and very great ſteps of defection from the Principles and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes of the once famous Church of Scotland, as indeed they are. And if our hearing and Joyning with them, will Inferr a Concurrence with their Courſe, A participation of their Guilt: And a rendring of us obnoxious to the Judgments to which breach of Covenant is Lyable: Since it is ſuch a Communion, as in the preſent Circumſtances is Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by all to be a <hi>Teſsera</hi> of Incorporation with them, and a ſigne of Approbation of their way, with which all muſt be Interpreted Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters that are not Contradicters. And Lykwiſe a laying doun of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Teſtimony, before the Courſes Teſtifyed againſt be forſaken, as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153370:6"/>none will deny. Then we ſee not, How any Honeſt man, Zealous Chriſtian, or Faithfull Miniſter can Condemn us, for Declaring our cheerfull Reſolution, in the Lords ſtrength, to ſtand off, and not to Concurr with them in this their New and ſtrange way, by hearing them, paying their Stipends, obſerving their Faſt or Thanksgiving days, Compearing before their Kirk-Seſſions, Preſbyteries, Synods, Generall Aſſemblies or the Lyke. But on the Contrarie, To proteſt and Teſtify againſt the Conſtitution of theſe Eccleſiaſtick Meetings; In Regard they are made up of ſuch a corrupt mixture of Members. Some of them having embraced <hi>Indulgences;</hi> Some having given <hi>Bonds</hi> to the Councell <hi>not to preach for an Indefinite or Longer or Shorter tyme;</hi> Some having ordinarly heard and Communicated with the <hi>Curates;</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me having come under ſinfull <hi>Bonds of Peace</hi> and <hi>Oaths of Aleigance,</hi> and the lyke, to the perſecuting Adverſaries, Repugnant to the Oath of our Covenants. Againſt the breaches of which Covenant, We Teſtifie, And againſt all the Injuries and Affronts that have been or are offered to the ſame by the Miniſters in Scotland, in not preaching the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Obligation of them, nor Renewing them; Neither diſcovering particularly the breaches thereof: Yea many not once mentioning them in the Engadgments which they Require of parents, when they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent their Children to Baptiſme, or in their Licencing and Ordaining of perſons to that Holy Function of the Miniſtery. Oh! How Aſtoniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing! The like not to be heard among the Heathen; That theſe So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Vows and Covenants ſhould not only be Scorned, derided, and openly burnt, and made a Capital Cryme to oun them, by Open &amp; Avowed Adverſaries; But alſo caſt by and buried by the Miniſters of the Church of Scotland, called Presbyterians. A Covenant, without the Swearing of which, none was capable of the meaneſt Employment either in Church or State. A Covenant, to which Chriſts witneſses did alwayes Adhere: and for which they did Suffer &amp; Contend. That Covenant, which the Repreſentatives of Church &amp; State in the three Kingdoms, Did Solemnly Swear and Subſcribe for themſelves and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; Of which the Obligation, either to the Duty or Puniſhment, continues Indiſpenſible upon the Generation; which for the Moral E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of its <hi>Matter,</hi> the Formality of its <hi>Manner,</hi> the Importance of its <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> the Holineſſe of its <hi>Solemn Engadgment,</hi> and the Glory of its <hi>Ends,</hi> No power on Earth can diſannull, Diſable or diſpenſe. That Covenant, which was juſtly thought a fitt and excellent <hi>Mean,</hi> not only to ſtrengthen and fortifie the Kingdoms againſt the Common Enemy of the True Reformed Religion, Publick peace and. proſperity; But alſo, to acquire the favour of Almighty God towards the three Kingdoms of Scotland, England and Ireland, as is expreſt in <hi>the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Lords and Commons for taking of the Covenant</hi> Dated <hi>February</hi> 20. 1643. <hi>Surely then, the Authors and Chief Inſtruments of the breaches of that Covenant, are to be looked upon as thoſe that ſtrengthen the hands of the Common Enemy, and provoke the wrath of Almighty God againſt theſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153370:6"/>Kingdoms. And if by the Declaration of both Kingdoms, Joyned in Arms Anno</hi> 1643. <hi>Such as would not take the Covenant, are declared to be Publick Enemies to their Religion and Countrey, and to be Cenſured &amp; puniſhed as Publick Adverſaries &amp; Malignants: Who ſeeth not now a ſtrange falling away from theſe firſt Principles &amp; Profeſſions among thoſe who either Magnify &amp; Cry up, or at the leaſt Connive at and Comply with ſuch as have not taken the Covenant, Yea are known Enemies to it?</hi> Yet notwithſtanding, Theſe ſame Enemies have been Complyed with and Connived at, by many Miniſters, in their taking <hi>Oaths</hi> Impoſed by them, Repugnant, we ſay, to the Oath of our Covenants. And others of them having go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne on in ſundry other ſteps of Defection: and to no ſmall Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſts more faithfull Sufferers and Witneſſes; Moſt part ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Addreſſed for, and accepted of the late Anti-chriſtian <hi>Toleration:</hi> And to this day are treading the ſame paths that lead to Defection, and to a deteſtable Indifferencie and Neutrality in the Lords Matters; without any ſhaddow of their Cordial Abandoning ſuch Wofull Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: But on the Contrary, a <hi>wyping of the mouth, and ſaying, We have done no Evil:</hi> A Faſting, praying and Giving Thanks for ſucceſſe and Proſperity to thoſe <hi>who have devoured Jacob, and laid his habitation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate;</hi> Under whoſe ſhaddow they Enjoy this unhallowed eaſe, as if they were delivered to retain and mentain all theſe Abominations. Can ſuch a work be of God? Can tender Zealous ſouls Concurr with it in Faith? Or, Can it ſtand? Which hath its foundation laid upon the Ruines of TRUTH? Such a Superſtructure, as <hi>building up ZION with blood, and Jeruſalem with Iniquitie.</hi> Such meaſures, being boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the decrees of Gods Enemies. And ſuch Workers, who by the word of God &amp; decrees of our Church, would be ſuſpended, if not depoſed from their Office, and brought in as delinquents to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo Cenſure, and not as Conſtituent Members of a Judicatorie. In regard they have yeelded up the Liberties of the Church into the hands and will of her Enemies: and in regard they carry on a Courſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, contrary to the Scriptures, our Covenants, and the Acts and Conſtitutions of this Church. We ſay again, upon theſe grounds, We, in our places &amp; ſtations, Teſtify againſt all that they may Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de or Determine in theſe their Eccleſiaſtick Courts, by <hi>Acts, Ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Declarations, Sentences, Cenſures</hi> or <hi>Commiſſions &amp;c.</hi> that ſhall be made or Given out by them: And proteſts that the ſamen may be voyd and null, and not Interpreted as binding to the Church of Scotland. But let none think, that what we have here ſaid can be Interpreted to be a vilipending or Rejecting of the Free, Lawfull, and Rightly Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Courts of Chriſt: For we do Acknowledge ſuch to have been among the firſt and moſt effectuall Means Appointed of God, for preſerving the purity, and Advancing the Power of Reformation in the Church; The ſweet fruits and bleſſed effects wherof this Church hath ſomtyme Enjo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed: which we have been endeavouring after, and are this day lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:153370:7"/>
            <p>We Deteſt and Abhorr that principle, of <hi>Caſting off the Miniſtrie,</hi> wherewith we are maliciouſly Calumniated, by thoſe who Labour to faſten upon us the Odious Names of <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Separatiſts, Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſers of the Goſpel</hi> and the like. But as herein they bewray their enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Cauſe we oun; So, till they bring their oun Principles and Practiſes, and ours both, and try them by the Law and the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the meaſuring Line of the Sanctuary, The Word of God, and the Practiſe of this Church when the Lord kept houſe with her, and rejoyced over her as a Brydgroom over the Bryde, They can never prove us <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> or <hi>Separatiſts</hi> from the Kirk of Scotland, upon the Account of our <hi>Non-Union</hi> with the Backſlyding Multitude therein. And herein we may have a ſure and well grounded hope, that when the Lord ſhall decide the Controverſy in the favours of Truth; In that Day, <hi>Union</hi> in Truth &amp; Duty, and <hi>Separation</hi> ſinfully conſidered, will be otherwiſe applyed than now they are. Beſides, we may ſay (without boaſting) we ſuppoſe it may be gathered from what we have done for the faithfully preached Goſpell, and what Love and Reſpect we have ky<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed towards faithfull Miniſters, whilſt ſuch, what our Carriage to them would yet be if we had them. Yea, we are ſo far from having any ſtated Prejudice (as ſome fooliſhly think) at any of them, for whatever their ſtrayings have been, either as Miniſters or Chriſtians; That we <hi>Declare</hi> by theſe Preſents, whenever the Lord ſhall ſend us ſuch, as out of Love to God, zeal for his Publick Concernments, and Conſcience of their Duty, will kyth their Reſentment of their former Backſlydings and Defections, by Condemning and forſaking the ſame, and ſatiſfy the offended Conſciences of the Lords People, by their Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Declaring the mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of God Faithfully &amp; Freely, and the Peoples Duty in order to the past and Preſent Courſes of the time; Keeping nothing back that may be profitable for our building up in Holineſſe, our manadging a Teſtimony for Chriſt, againſt all the forementioned or the like ſteps of Defection, and that the ſame may be Faithfully Tranſmitted to the ſucceeding Generations; That they may know what the Lord hath done for our Land, and may not be like their Fathers, a race not right in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eart with God, Unſteadfaſt and Perfidious in his Covenant. Upon theſe CONDITIONS, and Upon Removal of Juſt Exceptions, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Promiſe our hearty Concurrence with them, in hearing them, and to doe every other thing, that Precept or former Practiſe to Miniſters in the like Caſe, can oblidge Perſons in our Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances to doe to or for their Faithfull Leaders, to whom they may ſafely, without ſcruple, Commit the Charge of their ſouls. Withall Proteſting, that this our Declaration may be a ſtanding Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to all the Lies, Reproaches, Miſinformations, or Miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whatſoever, that ſhall be brought in againſt us in time coming, by whatſoever Party or Perſons, upon the Account of our Non-confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derating with them; Seing what we here Require, is both Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious &amp; Reaſonable; And ſeing what we oun, is of no new Extraction:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153370:7"/>But was eſteemed Truth before we had a tongue to ſpeak for it; and, we hope, ſhall be ſo, when its Enemies &amp; betrayers ſhall want a mouth to ſpeak againſt it.</p>
            <p>And now, having thus Declared our Teſtimony in as Compendious and Innocent a way, as the Nature and Circumſtances of it will Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. As we are not altogether Ignorant what Acceptation it ſhall find from Perſons of all tempers to whoſe hands it may come; So eſpecially from thoſe Miniſters, Maſter ALEXANDER SCHIELDS, Maſter THOMAS LINNING, Maſter WILLIAM BOYD, and others their Accomplices, who have lately gone from us and left us, after the Lord (in his mercy to us) had fruſtrate their deſigne of Precipitating us into a Confederacy with all thoſe to whom the Nations are ſaying, A CONFE DE RACY, by Regimenting and Uniting with the deſtroyers and betrayers of the Cauſe, and that both in Church and State; and caſting in our Lots, and Interweaving our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts with theirs; As they had done with many of our Brethren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and alſo with many of our ſelves, which this day we deſire to mourn for, And longs for that day, wherein we may Confeſſe the ſame before a Competent &amp; Faithfull Judicatory. But if we durſt ſay, that what we have here done, was not intended to pleaſe our ſelves, ſo neither to give Juſt ground of Irritation or Stumbling to any of the Lords People. And as for the wicked, who know not at what they Stumble, we may warrantably ſay, It was not deſigned to Pleaſe them, be the Event what it will. Only this, To let the Indifferent and Lukwarm Party on the one hand know, that the Lord is keeping up a handfull to witneſſe for him, againſt their paſt and Preſent Rotten Courſes of Defection, Notwithſtanding their cutting off the Hair, and putting out the eyes of theſe three Miniſters before-mentioned, and carying them in their Printed <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Letters</hi> through the Nations, as Trophees of their victory over them; as men whoſe former Lives &amp; Doctrine had been Contrary to the former Rules and Principles of this Church, nouriſhing and encouraging Schiſme, Diviſion &amp; Defection, and their former Teſtimonies made up, in many things, of ſeverall Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory groſs miſtakes, uncharitable and Injurious Reflections ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding rather to kindle Contentions, than remove Diviſions. All which are plainly Inſinuated in their Act, Called. <hi>The Proceedings of the Aſſembly annent Maſter Linning and others.</hi> Thereby labouring, through them, to reach a blow to the Cauſe of God, and to all the faithfull Witneſſes and Witneſſings of the poor Remnant with whom they were once embarked. And that the Malignant Party may likewiſe know, that we look upon them as the Murtherers of our dear brethren, whoſe blood, as it is precious in Gods ſight, ſo no humane power can Indemnifie; for though it be Gods glory to pardon, yet mans duty and glory is, to Adminiſter Juſtice Impartially. We are not changed from our former Principles and Intentions, but our Cauſe is the ſame, whatever thoſe who have fallen off from us may plead for. And Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153370:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>we deſire all Perſons, of whatſoever new Party they be, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or other, that would appear more Refined than the reſt, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Act ſeparately from our Enemies and Antagoniſts, whilſt yet really Incorporate with them, and carrying on their deſignes more effectually, though more ſmoothly, and Inſtrumentall to break and Divide us more than any, as if purpoſely ſent forth by the Reſt for that effect; Not to miſtake us, as if what we have ſaid in order to the Reſt, were not applicable to them. But on the Contrary, that we look upon their Courſe, as Accompanyed with many Aggravations that others are not Capable of. And ſo, as more loathſome to God, ought to be the more Deteſtable to us. And as for Neutraliſts, who account it wiſdom to Condemn all, and Pretend to ſide with none, we referr them to the laſt Article of the <hi>Solemne League and Covenant</hi> (without forgetting the reſt) Namely, <hi>That we ſhall Aſſiſt and Defend all that enter into this League and Covenant, in the mentaining and Purſuing thereof, and ſhall not ſuffer our ſelves Directly nor Indirectly, by whatſoever Combination, Perſwaſion or Terrour, to be Divided or withdrawn from this bleſſed Union &amp; Conjunction; Whether to make Defection to the Contrary Part, or to give our ſelves to a Deteſtable Indifferency and Neutrality in this Cauſe.</hi> According to which Article, mens Reality and Integrity in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant will be Manifeſt and Demonſtrable, as well by their Ommiſſions as by their Commiſſions; as well by their not doing good as by their doing of evil. He that is not with us, is againſt us; and he that gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not with us, Scattereth. And whatever our Complaints be this day, toſſed with Tempeſts and not Comforted; Yet we hope he hath thoughts of Peace and Purpoſe of mercy towards us. We do not mourn as thoſe without hope: But we will bear the Indignation of the Lord, becauſe we have ſinned againſt him, Untill he plead our Cauſe and Execute Judgment for us. He hath lifted Up our Enemies that their fall may be the greater: and that He may caſt them down into deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ever. He will make his Cauſe to Triumph at laſt, over all Oppoſition, and the Enemies foot to ſlyde in due time: And ſo put a new ſong of Praiſe in the mouths of all the faithfull friends and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the LAMB.</p>
            <p>Therefore we Appoint and Ordain, that Incontinently ye our Emiſſaries paſs upon the tenth day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1692 years, unto the <hi>Mercat Croſs</hi> of SANQHAIR, and there by open Proclamation make Intimation of this our <hi>Declaration,</hi> leaving Coppies of the ſamen Affixed upon the forſaid Mercat Croſſe and other patent places of the Kingdom neceſſary. Given at....... upon the tenth day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1692 Years.</p>
            <p>LET KING JESUS REIGNE AND LET ALL HIS ENEMIES BE SCATTERED.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
